<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Ashwin's Chronicles - Blog</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/blog.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2019-01-01T00:00:00+05:30</updated><entry><title>Make a Github Pages blog with Pelican</title><link href="/gh-pages-with-pelican.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-01-01T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2019-01-01T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Ashwin</name></author><id>tag:None,2019-01-01:/gh-pages-with-pelican.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Make a Github Pages blog with Pelican&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Github, worlds leading  hosting service for Git repositories  offers a simple, elegant website solution. It allows its users to  store page content in a git repository along with their code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this blog post ill walk you through the process of setting up …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Make a Github Pages blog with Pelican&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Github, worlds leading  hosting service for Git repositories  offers a simple, elegant website solution. It allows its users to  store page content in a git repository along with their code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this blog post ill walk you through the process of setting up a website by combining Pelican with Github Pages. Pelican is a simple python utility that lets you create beautiful weblogs using just text files. In other words its a static-site generator. I have chosen Pelican over other static-site generators as Pelican unlike its counter parts is based on python hence initial  setup takes literally no time.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Github"></category><category term="Pelican"></category><category term="gh-pages"></category></entry><entry><title>The Journey Begins</title><link href="/the-journey-begins.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-06-18T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2018-06-18T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Ashwin</name></author><id>tag:None,2018-06-18:/the-journey-begins.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In which the author writes their first blog post.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Thanks for joining me!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am Ashwin Kumar K, a Dual Degree BE – Int. MSc Physics at BITS Pilani KK Birla Goa campus (Batch of 2017).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the first post of this site where I intend to post some of my works related to the field of Science and Engineering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had always wanted to publish some of my projects and experiments on a public platform so that people working on similar projects can give and take ideas. It also serves as a way to showcase the experience that I have gained while doing such projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I intend to post details of projects or experiments that I have performed mostly in the field of Science and Engineering as I complete them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take a trip down my memory lane. I hope to see you around!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Random"></category></entry></feed>